# Daniel Nichols Full-Stack Developer

herrnichols@gmail.com | LinkedIn: Daniel-Nichols | GitHub: DanielCNichols | Portfolio

# **Summary**

A full-stack developer and accomplished educator, I am passionate about using technology as a driver to deepen our insights and improve our quality of life. My five years of small business and nonprofit management experience along with my background as an educator gives me a unique perspective on web development. I am looking for the opportunity to use my skills and experience as part of a goal-oriented, highly collaborative development team.

### Technical skills

Front End: JavaScript ES6, React, jQuery, HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap

Back End: Node.js, Express, Relational Databases(PostgreSQL), MongoDB, TDD with Mocha and Chai, Restful API

Additional: Git, GitHub, Slack, Windows, Linux, Mac, Heroku, Enzyme, Jasmine,

# **Projects**

#### ChoreRunner

## GitHub (Client) | GitHub (API) | Live

A household management app that makes assigning and tracking household chores easy for parents and fun for kids. Users create a household, add members, create tasks, and award points to members for completing chores. Members of each household compete for the highest score, and as they accumulate points, gain levels and win badges to show their rank.

Technologies: PostgreSQL, NodeJS, CSS3, React

#### CleverGerman

#### GitHub (Client) | GitHub (API) | Live

CleverGerman is a spaced-repetition application that helps students master basic German vocabulary. As users are introduced to new words, the app assesses their proficiency with each word and adapts to give students more practice on tough-to-learn words.

Technologies: PostgreSQL, NodeJS, CSS3, React

#### Marks

#### GitHub (Client) | GitHub (API) | Live

Marks is a bookmarking application inspired by the ubiquitous text editor, Vim, with stylistic cues taken from the fabulous Monokai color scheme. Simple and straightforward, Marks allows the user to create their own account, log in, and quickly get started saving their favorite websites.

Technologies: MongoDB, NodeJS, CSS3, React

## **Appalachian Trail Quiz**

## GitHub Live

Inspired by my own successful "thru-hike" of the Appalachian Trail in 2013, this app tests the user on their knowledge of AT culture and lore through ten multiple choice questions, ranking the user on their performance at the end of the quiz.

Technologies: HTML 5, CSS3, Javascript, jQuery

# **Professional Experience**

## Teacher, 6th Grade English

July 2016-July 2019

C.W. Stanford Middle School, Hillsborough, NC

- Built strong relationships with a diverse cohort of over 130 students and their families each year
- Implemented data-driven strategies to coach students of all levels to success, meeting or exceeding expected growth measures each year
- Collaborated with a dedicated team of educators to create cross-curricular learning opportunities for students
- Planned and prepared engaging instructional activities to facilitate an effective learning experience

## **Operations Manager**

Kidznotes, Durham, NC

October 2013-March 2016

- Managed program-related processes to ensure a safe and orderly learning environment for 230 students aged K-12
- Supervised a staff of 26 faculty members at six program sites
- Created and managed faculty and program schedules, including 40 class sessions and group rehearsals per week
- Prepared grant reports for funding from foundations including D'Addario, The Mead Family, and the Mary Norris Preyer Fund, receiving awards totaling over \$70,000

## **Account Manager/Brand Management**

High Strung Violins & Guitars, Durham, NC

June 2010-April 2013

Graduated: May 2010

- Managed a rental program totaling over 700 accounts and 1000 instruments
- Independently proposed and implemented a Point of Sale system to assist in inventory management

## **Education**

Thinkful January 2020

Full-Stack Web Development Program

- Learned industry best practices and practical software development standards with a focus on HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, ¡Query, Node.js, React, and algorithms & data structures.
- Created and deployed mobile-first applications while learning new languages and frameworks by collaborating several hours every week with a senior web developer.

Bachelor of Science, Business Administration

University of North Carolina at Greensboro

Minor: Economics

Study Abroad: Universität Mannheim, January 2009 - June 2009

# **Achievements and Special Activities**

Appalachian Trail Thru-Hiker, Class of 2013

Start date: April 14, 2013, Springer Mountain, GA

End Date: Sept. 21, 2013, Katahdin, ME